BETH: Throughout life we are all
exposed to different life events
and react to them in different ways.
When autism is added into the
equation the problems are much
greater for all concerned.
Individuals with autism find
change and transition difficult
and need that extra support.
When those changes are life events that
affect the family dynamic, they can cause
a great deal of upheaval, impacting on
the individual with autism by potentially
destroying their routines and pulling
their safety net out from under them.
JOE: The death of a family member can
have a devastating effect on everyone
in the family, however, individuals with
autism react to death and experience
the grieving process differently.
They have difficulty connecting with their
emotions and may not cry, or they may show
a delayed or extreme emotional response.
They may potentially experience
an increase in their sensory
sensitivities, meltdowns or shutdowns
and find it harder to organise,
plan and concentrate on tasks.
They may have difficulty
understanding how to behave in
social situations such as funerals
and seeing other family members cry.
BETH: The birth of a sibling may cause
a range of problems with individuals
with autism such as finding it
difficult to ask questions about
the pregnancy and birth process or
express their emotions about the birth.
Having a new baby in the house can bring
its own problems, what will it be like?
changes in rules and routines, or changes
in caregivers whilst their mother is
in hospital or looking after the baby.
They may struggle with sensory input
from the new sounds and smells a
baby will bring and the behaviour
of the baby may confuse them.
JOE: Major life changes will happen
with education, from starting nursery,
through primary and secondary school
and maybe college and University, and on
leaving school they need to be prepared
for work and for adulthood which can
also bring some dramatic changes.
BETH: Moving house can take them
from what they see as a secure
place to somewhere that may have no
meaning to them, even though it may
contain the same things and people.
If the place they are moving to is
totally different, such as somewhere
away from the family, where they may live
independently or with others with similar
disorders they may struggle to settle.
They may, however, find going off on
their own and making new relationships
exciting, but this will possibly
challenging for others who have to
support them through through the process.
JOE: Minor or smaller transitions can
affect them such as changing class
at the end of each year or moving
up a grade in a swimming class.
Even daily transitions, moving
from one activity to another, from
place to place, or person to person
can have a great impact on them.
These ongoing transitions may not
seem like a major difficulty to
others, but they can have a dramatic
effect on individuals with autism.
BETH: The way such changes and
transitions are managed can make a big
difference to an individual with autism’s
well-being, ability to learn skills,
make progress and build relationships
in the future and possibly help
with the more major changes in life.